Guide to the Frederick Stoever Dickson Collection Regarding Henry Fielding
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Frederick Stoever Dickson collection regarding Henry Fielding
1733-1937
1900-1922
GEN MSS 511
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
12.2
(24 boxes)
The Frederick Stoever Dickson Collection regarding Henry Fielding consists of correspondence, writings and subject files documenting research and scholarship on Henry Fielding. There are two series: Frederick Stoever Dickson Papers and Material from Other Sources. The Frederick Stoever Dickson Papers consist of three subseries: Correspondence, Writings and Subject Files. Correspondence consists chiefly of letters to Dickson from publishers, bookdealers, journal editors, libraries and Fielding scholars. Writings includes draft and printed versions of work by Dickson and a considerable amount of periodical literature on Fielding. Subject Files contain research material, chiefly bibliographic clippings, on Fielding. Material from Other Sources consists of two subseries: Correspondence and Writings. Correspondence contains letters from Dickson to Wilbur Lucius Cross and third-party correspondence between Cross and others. Writings consists of a small amount of periodical literature on Fielding.
Dickson, Frederick Stoever, 1850-1925
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Frederick Stoever Dickson Collection regarding Henry Fielding was acquired by gift from Frederick Stoever Dickson. Additional gifts have been made by Wilbur Lucius Cross and Gerard Edward Jensen.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research. Box 5: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
FREDERICK STOEVER DICKSON (1850-1925)
Frederick Stoever Dickson was born June 24, 1850, in Utica, New York to Rev. Hugh Sheridan Dickson, a graduate of Princeton Theological Seminary and a Presbyterian minister, and Sarah Margaret (Stoever) Dickson. Dickson attended Yale University with the Class of 1871, studied law in Philadelphia from 1871-74, was admitted to the Pennsylvania bar in 1874, and practiced law in Philadelphia until 1898. He then pursued various management, banking and investment interests in Ohio and Pennsylvania from 1900-1913, during which time he was president of telephone companies in Cleveland, manager of the Cleveland office of the New York banking and brokerage firm of A. O. Brown & Company, and president of The Abrasive Company of Bricksburg, Philadelphia. He lived in New York City from 1913-24 and died December 1, 1925, in Philadelphia.
Dickson produced published and unpublished work on Henry Fielding, William Makepeace Thackeray and other subjects. He is the author of An Analysis of Blackstone's Commentaries (1874) and An Analysis of Kent's Commentaries (1876), on American law, And the Wilderness Blossomed (1901), a description of his summer home in Maine, Thackeray in the United States (1904), and contributions to Fielding literature in The Library, Yale Review, Notes and Queries and other journals. He also compiled indexes to Fielding's novels. Dickson collected work by and about both Fielding and Thackeray, and he donated his Fielding collection of approximately 2,000 volumes to the Yale University Library in 1913.
For additional biographical information on Frederick Stoever Dickson see the Yale University Obituary Record of Graduates of Yale College (1926). For a summary description of Dickson's Fielding collection see the Wilbur Lucius Cross essay in The Yale University Library Gazette (1927).
Scope and Contents
The Frederick Stoever Dickson Collection regarding Henry Fielding consists of correspondence, writings and subject files documenting research and scholarship on Henry Fielding (1707-54). The collection spans the years 1733-1937, with the bulk of the material dating from 1900-1920.
The collection is housed in 24 boxes and organized into two series: Frederick Stoever Dickson Papers and Material from Other Sources. Boxes 23-24 contain Oversize material and Restricted Fragile Papers respectively.
Series I, Frederick Stoever Dickson Papers, is organized into three subseries: Correspondence, Writings and Subject Files.
The Correspondence subseries, housed in boxes 1-2, consists predominantly of letters to Dickson from publishers, bookdealers, journal editors, libraries and Fielding scholars. Prominent scholars represented are Wilbur L. Cross, John Paul de Castro, Austin Dobson, Gerard Edward Jensen, Alfred William Pollard and John Edwin Wells. The letters from Cross, a Yale professor, discuss the donation of Dickson's Fielding collection to the Yale University Library and, in general, Fielding research. Letters from Dickson to Cross are located in Series II, Material from Other Sources. Dickson's gift to Yale is also well documented in correspondence from University Librarian Andrew Keogh.
The Writings subseries, housed in boxes 3-7, is organized into eight subseries: Articles and Essays, Biographical Material, Notes, Open Letters, Presentations, Reviews, Writings of Others Related to Fielding and Writings of Others not Related to Fielding. Previously unprocessed material has been incorporated into both the Writings and Subject Files subseries. In the Writings there are draft and printed versions of works by Dickson and a considerable amount of periodical literature by the Fielding scholars with whom Dickson corresponded in the first two decades of the 20th century, as well as from English sources dating from the mid to late 19th century. In addition to those already mentioned, there is work by Thomas Keightley, Sir Walter Scott and William Makepeace Thackeray. The bulk of the secondary literature consists of clippings. Reprints and offprints are noted in the folder description.
The Subject Files, housed in boxes 8-21, consist of research material on Fielding and, more broadly, 18th-19th century English literature. The Subject Files are arranged by type of material and include bibliographic material, clippings and maps.
The Bibliographic material consists of index cards and clippings of citations for titles housed in 3 1/2" by 6" envelopes. The organization of these files, established either by Dickson or earlier processing, has been preserved and includes sections for Books, Miscellanies, Art, Works of Others, Periodicals, the Catalogue of the Law Library of Henry Fielding, the Catalogue of the Miscellaneous Library of Henry Fielding, and a Card Catalog for Fielding.
Books, which contains citations for several of Fielding's novels and The Journal of a Voyage to Lisbon, is housed in boxes 8-9 and arranged first by title and then chronologically for each work. The Miscellanies section contains citations for other works by Fielding, such as plays, letters, manuscripts, journals and collections. Miscellanies, housed in boxes 9-12, is arranged under the following categories: Works by Fielding, Works Possibly by Fielding, Works Erroneously Attributed to Fielding, Letters and Manuscripts, Theater Editions and Works. Art, housed in box 12, is a small section of citations for artwork and illustrations in works by Fielding, largely his novels, arranged alphabetically by the artist's name. Works of Others, housed in boxes 12-17, is arranged alphabetically by author or title. Periodicals, housed in boxes 18-19 and arranged alphabetically by title, contains citations for journal literature by and about Fielding, including Champion, The Covent-Garden Journal, The True Patriot, and The Jacobite's Journal. The two catalog listings, Catalogue of the Law Library of Henry Fielding and Catalogue of the Miscellaneous Library of Henry Fielding, appear to be listings of books owned by Fielding in his lifetime. They are both housed in box 19 and arranged alphabetically by author. The Card Catalog, housed in box 20, also provides citations for works by and about Fielding, with emphasis on Fielding's novels.
The remaining Fielding materials are housed in box 21. Clippings provide biographical information on Fielding, as well as bibliographical information on Fielding and Fielding scholarship. There is discussion of the Fielding name and ancestry, publicity for commemorative events, auction sales and publications, and reviews of editions and theatrical productions. Here, too, the general organization provided either by Dickson or earlier processing has been preserved. For the most part, clippings are organized by journal title when three or more clippings are present. Clippings are arranged chronologically within folders.
Fieldingiana includes, among other small items, a facsimile copy of Henry and Charlotte Fielding's signatures and a list of "Framed Fielding pictures" in the Fielding collection.
Maps contains printed maps identified as illustrating publications of Tom Jones. Most maps are from The London Magazine and represent areas in England. The maps are arranged by title.
Series II, Material from Other Sources, housed in box 22, is organized into two subseries, Correspondence and Writings. The correspondence is a gift from Wilbur L. Cross and his estate and the writings are a gift from Gerard Edward Jensen. The bulk of the letters in the Correspondence subseries are from Dickson to Cross and concern, among other subjects, the gift of Dickson's Fielding collection to the University and preparation of a Fielding bibliography. Letters span the years 1913-22. There is a small amount of third party correspondence between Cross and others in 1920-21 regarding an endowment fund for the maintenance of Fielding's tomb in Lisbon.
The Writings subseries consists of journal literature on Fielding dating from 1922-37.
Oversize material, housed in box 23, includes items from Series I. Restricted Fragile Papers are housed in box 24.
English literature -- 18th century; English literature -- 19th century; Booksellers' catalogues; Clippings (information artifacts); Authors; Cross, Wilbur L. (Wilbur Lucius), 1862-1948; De Castro, J. Paul (John Paul), 1874-1944; Dickson, Frederick Stoever, 1850-1925; Dobson, Austin, 1840-1921; Fielding, Henry, 1707-1754; Hughes, Helen Sard, 1882-1955; Jensen, Gerard Edward, 1884-; Keightley, Thomas, 1789-1872; Keogh, Andrew, 1869-1953; Pollard, Alfred W. (Alfred William), 1859-1944; Scott, Walter, 1771-1832; Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863; Wells, John Edwin, 1875-1943
- Frederick Stoever Dickson Papers, 1733-1931; Series I; 10.11; (21 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Frederick Stoever Dickson Papers, is organized into three subseries: Correspondence, Writings and Subject Files.
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - "A" General, 1912 Mar, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "B" General, 1907-16 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - B. and J. F. Meehan
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Meehan, John Francis, Box 2, folder 61
    - Blanchard, Frederic T. (Frederic Thomas), 1916 Sep 11 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Boston Athenaeum. Library, 1912-16 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - British Museum. Dept. of Printed Books, 1907-19, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Includes list of works ascribed to Fielding
      See also: Pollard, Alfred W. (Alfred William), Box 2, folder 72
    - Brown, William, 1912-13 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "C" General, 1905-13 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Charles E. Lauriat Company, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Charles Scribner's Sons, 1911, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Cross, Wilbur L. (Wilbur Lucius), 1911-21, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10-29)
      Includes notes from Austin Dobson and enclosures from Ernest W. Brown and Gerard Edward Jensen
    - "D" General, 1911-17 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - De Castro, John Paul, 1915-21 (Box 1, Folder 31-34)
      Includes letter from Dickson
    - Dobell, Bertram, 1912-18 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Dobson, Austin, 1912-16, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 36)
      Includes letter from Dickson and clipping
    - "E" General, 1912-16 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - "G" General, 1906-17 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - G. E. Stechert & Co., 1912, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Ginn and Company, 1914-16 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Gregory, George, 1907-13, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - "H" General, 1911-13 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Harvard University. Library, 1912, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 43)
      Includes list of Fielding editions
    - Havens, Munson Aldrich, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Hughes, Helen Sard, 1919 Oct 25 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Humphreys, May, 1920-21 (Box 2, Folder 46)
      Includes carbon from Arthur Swann
    - James Rimell & Son, 1912-13 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Jensen, Gerard Edward, 1913-19 (Box 2, Folder 48-50)
    - John E. Scopes & Co., 1912, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Keogh, Andrew
      See: Yale University. Library Box 2, folders 90-94
    - "L" General, 1903-16, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Library of Congress, 1907, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 53)
      Includes memos
    - Lounsbury, Thomas Raynesford, 1903-15 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Ludwig Rosenthal's Antiquariaat, 1911-12, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - "M" General, 1905-16 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - McCabe W. Gordon (William Gordon), 1914 Mar 10 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - McCulloch C. C. (Champe Carter), 1914 May 28 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Marks, Harry F., 1916-17 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Massey, Edward, 1911-16 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Meehan, John Francis, 1907-13, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Millard, Clara, 1910-14, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Milligan, Joseph, 1911-12 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Miner, William Harvey
      See: Torch Press Book Shop, Box 2, folder 81
    - Modern Language Association of America, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Morton, J. Metcalfe, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - "N" General, 1916-17 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - National Shawmut Bank, Boston, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - The North American Review, 1912-13 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Noyes, Perley H., 1921 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - "O" General, 1916 Nov 29 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - "P" General, 1916 Dec 14 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Pollard, Alfred W. (Alfred William), 1916-17 (Box 2, Folder 72)
      See also: British Museum. Dept. of Printed Books, Box 1, folder 5
    - "R" General, 1917 Jun 7 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Rice, Grantland (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - "S" General, 1910-16 (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - Saintsbury, George, 1913 Apr 14 (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - Schwab, John Christopher, 1912-15 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Suckling & Co., 1906, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Sutton, Albert, 1912-15, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - "T" General, 1912-17 (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Torch Press Book Shop, 1907-12, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - "W" General, 1912-17 (Box 2, Folder 82)
      Includes copy of undated letter ascribed to W. M. Thackeray
    - Wells, John Edwin, 1911-17 (Box 2, Folder 83-85)
    - William Smith & Son, 1913, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - Williams, E., 1915-19, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 87-88)
    - "Y" General, 1920 May 8 (Box 2, Folder 89)
    - Yale University. Library, 1912-21, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 90-94)
      Includes enclosures from J. Pearson & Co. and Levin & Goldberg
    - Unidentified, 1915-16 (Box 2, Folder 95)
  - WRITINGS
    - Articles and Essays
      - "The Chronology of 'Tom Jones'"
        - Draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 96)
        - Printed version and offprint, The Library, 1917 Jul (Box 3, Folder 97)
      - "The Complete Works of Henry Fielding"
        - Draft, holograph, corrected, 1916 Apr 4 (Box 3, Folder 98)
        - Draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 99)
      - "The Early Editions of Fielding's Voyage to Lisbon and offprint, The Library, 1917 Jan (Box 3, Folder 100)
      - "Eighteenth Century Flash-Lights," holograph, corrected and signed (Box 3, Folder 101)
      - "Errors and Omission in 'Tom Jones'"
        - Draft, holograph, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 102)
        - Printed version, The Library, 1918 Jan (Box 3, Folder 103)
      - "The History of Tom Jones," holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 104)
      - "William Makepeace Thackeray and Henry Fielding," holograph, corrected and signed (Box 3, Folder 105)
    - Bibliographic Material
      - Book lists and notes, holograph and typescript (Box 3, Folder 106)
      - Critical and bibliographical notes, holograph, 1916, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 107)
      - Fielding bibliographies, holograph and typescript (Box 3, Folder 108)
      - Indexes
        - "Index to "Amelia"," holograph, bound, 1911 (Box 3, Folder 108a)
        - "Index to "Joseph Andrews"," holograph, bound, 1911 (Box 3, Folder 108b)
          Includes "An Index to Jonathon Wild, the Great" and "An Index to a Journey from this World to the Next"
        - "An Index to the History of Tom Jones, a Foundling," holograph, bound, 1913 (Box 4, Folder 108c)
        - "An Index to the Journal of a Voyage to Lisbon," holograph, bound, 1915-16 (Box 4, Folder 108d-108e)
      - Printed list of books by Henry Fielding, annotated, 1912 Mar 1 (Box 5, Folder 109)
    - Notes
      - [On Alfred Trumble], holograph and typescript, 1906-16, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 110)
      - [On the Genealogy of the Fielding Family], holograph, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 111)
      - [On The History of Tom Jones ], holograph and typescript, with clipping (Box 5, Folder 112)
      - [On A Voyage to Lisbon ], holograph and typescript, 1916, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 113)
        Includes holograph note attributed to W. L. Cross
    - Open Letters
      - "Can any of the Readers..." printed version, New York Times, 1906 Dec 15 (Box 5, Folder 114)
      - "The Chronology of Fielding's Voyage to Lisbon ," holograph, corrected and signed, 1916 Sep 25 (Box 5, Folder 115)
      - "The Chronology of 'Tom Jones'"
        - Draft, holograph, corrected, 1914 Apr 14 (Box 5, Folder 116)
        - Printed version, Notes and Queries, 1914 May 30 (Box 5, Folder 117)
      - "The Complete Works of Henry Fielding still to be hoped for," typescript carbon, 1903 Jul 31 (Box 5, Folder 118)
      - "Fielding Queries," printed version, Notes and Queries, 1914 Sep 12 (Box 5, Folder 119)
      - "Fielding's 'Tom Jones'," printed version, Notes and Queries, 1914 Sep 5 (Box 5, Folder 120)
      - "Fielding's Works," printed version, New York Times, 1903 Nov 21 (Box 5, Folder 121)
      - "The First Edition of "Tom Jones," typescript carbon, corrected, 1908 Sep 1 (Box 5, Folder 122)
      - "Henry Fielding," printed version, The Sun, 1912 Jan 27 (Box 5, Folder 123)
      - "Henry Fielding: Two Corrections," proof, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 124)
      - "Tom Jones on the Campaign," printed version, The Sun, 1912 Oct 8 (Box 5, Folder 125)
    - Presentations
      - "The Father of the English Novel," holograph, corrected, 1906 Apr 21 (Box 5, Folder 126)
    - Reviews
      - "The Author of Tom Jones," [On The History of Henry Fielding ], printed version, Yale Review, 1919 Jan (Box 5, Folder 127)
    - Writings of Others Related to Fielding
      - Aitken, G. A.
        - "Henry Fielding," biography, printed version, The Athenaeum, 1890 Feb 1 (Box 5, Folder 128)
      - Allibone, S. Austin (Samuel Austin)
        - "Fielding, Henry," biography, printed version, A Critical Dictionary of English Literature..., 1859 (Box 5, Folder 129)
      - Barrow, John, Sir
        - "Lives of the Novelists," review, printed version, The Quarterly Review, 1826 (Box 5, Folder 130)
      - Becker, Gustav
        - "Die Bedeutung des Wortes 'romantic' bei Fielding und Smollett," article, printed version, Archiv für das Studium neueren Sprachen und Literaturen, 1903 (Box 5, Folder 131)
      - Beers, Henry Augustin
        - "Retrospects of the Drama," article, printed version, The North American Review, 1907 Jul 19 (Box 5, Folder 132)
      - Boynton, H. W.
        - "Books Old and New," review of The Temple Fielding, printed version, The Atlantic Monthly, 1903 Mar (Box 5, Folder 133)
      - Bulloch, J. M.
        - "Fielding for the Girl of Eighteen," article, printed version, The Lamp, 1904 (Box 5, Folder 134)
      - Clarke, George Herbert
        - "To Master Henry Fielding," poem, printed version, The Outlook, 1904 Dec 3 (Box 5, Folder 135)
      - Cooper Frederic Taber
        - "Hogarth," article, printed version, The Bookman, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 136)
      - Cross, Wilbur L. (Wilbur Lucius)
        - "The Legend of Henry Fielding," article, printed version, Yale Review, 1918 Oct (Box 5, Folder 137)
        - "The New Fielding Collection," article, printed version, Yale Alumni Weekly, 1913 Feb 21 (Box 5, Folder 138)
        - "The Secret of Tom Jones," article printed version, The Bookman, 1918 Sep (Box 5, Folder 139)
      - De Castro, John Paul
        - "The Covent-Garden Journal," review, offprint from The Modern Language Review, inscribed, 1917 Apr (Box 5, Folder 140)
        - "Fielding Queries," open letter, printed version, Notes and Queries, 1914 Oct 10 (Box 5, Folder 141)
        - "Fielding's 'Tom Jones'," open letter, printed version, Notes and Queries, 1914 Jun 27 (Box 5, Folder 142)
        - "Fielding's 'Tom Jones': Its Geography," open letter, printed version, Notes and Queries, 1914 Sep 26 (Box 5, Folder 143)
        - "Henry Fielding's Last Voyage," article, printed version, The Library, 1917 Apr (Box 5, Folder 144)
          Includes "The Two 1755 Editions of Fielding's 'Journal of a Voyage to Lisbon,'" by Alfred W. Pollard
        - "The History of Henry Fielding," review, galley proof, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 145)
        - "The Printing of Fielding's Works," article, printed version, Trans- actions of the Bibliographical Society, 1921 Mar (Box 5, Folder 146)
      - Dobson, Austin
        - "The Convent-Garden Journal," article, printed version, The Living Age, 1901 Jun 29 (Box 6, Folder 147)
        - "Fielding and Andrew Millar," article, offprint from The Library, inscribed, 1916 Jul (Box 6, Folder 148)
        - "Fielding and Sarah Andrew," article, printed version, The Athenaeum, 1883 Jun 2 (Box 6, Folder 149)
        - "A Fielding Find," article, printed version, The National Review, 1911 Aug (Box 6, Folder 150)
        - "Fresh Facts about Fielding," article, printed version, Macmillan's Magazine, 1907 Apr (Box 6, Folder 151)
        - "Henry Fielding," article, printed version, Bibliographica, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 152)
        - "Henry Fielding," poem, printed version, The Athenaeum, 1883 Sep 8 (Box 6, Folder 153)
        - "A New Dialogue of the Dead," article, printed version and offprint, The National Review, signed, 1912 Dec (Box 6, Folder 154)
        - "The Taunton Bust of Fielding," article, printed version, The Magazine of Art, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 155)
      - Forman, H. Buxton (Harry Buxton)
        - "Richardson, Fielding, and the Andrews Family," article, printed version, The Fortnightly Review, 1901 Dec (Box 6, Folder 156)
      - Fornelli, Guido
        - "Enrico Fielding e la sua epoca," article, printed version, Annali delle Università toscane, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 157)
      - Godden, G. M.
        - Henry Fielding: A Memoir, book jacket, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 158)
        - "Henry Fielding: Some Unpublished Letters and Records," article, printed version, The Fortnightly Review, 1909 Nov (Box 6, Folder 159)
      - Hard, William
        - "The Woman's Invasion," article, printed version, Everybody's, 1909 Jan (Box 6, Folder 160)
      - Harrison, Frederic
        - "A Few Words about the Eighteenth Century," article, printed version, The Nineteenth Century, 1883 (Box 6, Folder 161)
      - Henley, William Ernest
        - "Henry Fielding," bound galley and page proofs, corrected, with proofreaders' marks, 1902-03 (Box 6, Folder 162)
          Includes "The descent of Henry Fielding" by Arthur Charles Fox-Davies, proofs, corrected
      - Hughes, Helen Sard
        - "A Dialogue--Possibly by Henry Fielding," article, offprint from Philological Quarterly, inscribed, 1922 Jan (Box 6, Folder 163)